Let's recall the problem at hand.
我们来看看我们面临的问题
We have an agent and environment.
我们有一个智能体和一个环境
Time has broken into discrete time steps,
时间被拆分为离散时间步
and every time step,
在每个时间步
the agent receives a reward and state from
智能体都从环境中获得一个奖励和状态
the environment and chooses an action to perform in response.
并选择一个响应动作
In this way, the interaction evolves as a sequence of states, actions, and rewards.
这样的话 互动变成一系列的状态 动作和奖励
In this lesson, we'll confine our attention to episodic tasks where the interaction
在这节课 我们将重点讨论阶段性任务
stops at some time step T when the agent encounters a terminal state.
当智能体在时间 T 遇到最终状态时 互动结束
And we refer to this sequence as an episode.
我们将这一过程称为一个阶段
For any episode, the agent's goal is to find
对于任何阶段 智能体的目标都是发现最优策略
the optimal policy in order to maximize expected cumulative reward.
以便最大化预期累积奖励
Towards this goal, we'll start with the prediction problem.
为此 我们将从预测问题开始
Given the policy, how might the agent estimate the value function for that policy?
给定策略后 智能体如何估算该策略的值函数？
Remember that the environment's dynamics are unknown to the agent.
注意 智能体不了解该环境的动态特性
So it will have to estimate the value function by interacting with the environment.
因此它需要通过与环境互动估算值函数
And in order to interact with the environment,
为了与环境互动
the agent needs to have a policy in mind.
智能体需要遵守一个策略
Now, it's possible to have one policy that we'd like to
我们可以用一个策略来进行评估
evaluate and a different policy to interact with the environment.
并用另一个策略来与环境互动
This is referred to as an off-policy method for the prediction problem.
称之为针对预测问题的离线策略方法
Off-policy methods entail some complexity that we'll save for later.
离线策略方法具有一定的复杂性 稍后我们将详细讲解
Instead, we'll start with an on policy method,
我们先讲解异同策略方法
where the agent interacts with the environment by following a policy,
即智能体通过遵循某个策略与环境互动
whose value function it would like to calculate.
并计算该策略的值函数
Before we go into the details of the algorithm,
在详细讲解该算法之前
let's look at a motivating example.
我们来看一个示例
Say we're working with an episodic task and the MDP has three states;
假设我们要处理一个阶段性任务 该 MDP 具有三个状态
X,Y, and Z, where Z has a terminal state.
X Y 和 Z 其中 Z 是最终状态
In case it helps to have a more visual understanding of the MDP,
为了更直观地理解该 MDP
you can think of it as a very,
你可以将问题看做一个
very small frozen world.
非常非常小的冰雪环境
Say states X and Y correspond to different locations in a snowy forest with
假设状态 X 和 Y 对应于一座白雪皑皑的森林中的不同地点
possible delights and terrors corresponding to possibly positive or negative reward.
森林中有令人愉悦和害怕的景象 对应于正面或负面奖励
Remember state Z is the terminal state and say it corresponds to a house in the forest.
状态 Z 是最终状态 对应于森林中的一个小屋
If the agent lands at the state,
如果智能体抵达该状态
it enters the house and the episode ends.
则进入小屋并结束这一阶段
Say there are two potential actions,
假设有两个潜在动作
up and down and similar to the frozen lake environment,
向上和向下 和冰冻湖泊环境相似
the world is slippery.
该环境非常光滑
So if the agent chooses action down,
如果智能体选择向下动作
at the next time step,
在下个时间步
there is some positive probability that it instead moves up or stays where it is.
有一定的概率表明它会向上移动或保持不动
Likewise, if it decides to go up then when it tries to move in that direction,
同样 如果它决定向上移动 当它尝试朝着该方向移动时
it might instead go down or again not move at all.
可能会向下移动或保持不动
And say we'd like to evaluate the policy where the agent chooses
假设我们要评估以下策略
action up in state X and action down in State Y.
智能体在状态 X 向上移动 在状态 Y 向下移动
Then towards this goal the agent could
智能体可以通过遵循该策略
interact with the environment by following this policy.
与环境互动
Say at the beginning of the interaction,
假设在一开始互动时
the agent observes state X,
智能体观察状态 X
then following the policy,
然后根据策略
it chooses action up, as a result.
选择向上动作
It receives a reward of negative two and the next state of Y.
结果获得奖励 -2 并进入下个状态 Y
Again, following the policy,
接着根据该策略
it chooses to go down,
选择向下动作
and as a result,
结果
gets a reward of zero and next state of Y.
获得奖励 0 并进入下个状态 Y
At this point, it follows the policy and chooses action down.
此刻 根据该策略选择向下动作
As a result, it gets a reward of three and reaches the terminal stage Z,
结果获得奖励 3 并抵达最终状态 Z
so the interaction ends.
互动结束
Say the agent interacts with the environment in two additional episodes.
假设智能体在另外两个阶段与环境互动
Then we can use these episodes to estimate the value function.
我们可以使用这些阶段估算值函数
Of course these three short episodes aren't really
当然 这三个简短的互动阶段
enough interaction for the agent to get a great understanding of the environment,
并不足以让智能体充分了解环境
but for now, let's assume that they're sufficient.
暂时先假设已足够
We'll begin with one state, say state X.
我们将从一个状态开始 例如状态 X
Then we look at all of the occurrences of state X and all of the episodes.
然后查看在所有阶段的状态 X 的所有状况
Then we just calculate the discounted return that followed after that state appeared.
接着计算在出现该状态之后的折扣回报
Say the discount is one so in other words, we won't discount.
假设折扣率是 1 即不折扣
Then in the case of the first episode,
对于第一个阶段
the return is negative two,
回报是 -2
plus zero, plus three or one.
加上 0 加上 3 结果为 1
And in the third episode,
在第三个阶段
the return is negative three plus three or zero.
回报是 -3 加上 3 结果为 0
The Monte Carlo prediction algorithm takes the average of
蒙特卡罗预测算法会对这些值取平均值
these values and plugs it in as an estimate for the value of state X.
并代入状态 X 的值估算方程中
In this case, the value of state X is estimated to be one half.
这里 状态 X 的估值为 1/2
This algorithm makes some intuitive sense.
该算法比较直观
Remember that the value of a state is defined to be
状态的值定义为
the expected return after that state is observed.
该状态之后的预期回报
And so the average return that was experienced by the agent makes for a good estimate.
因此智能体体验的平均回报是个很好的估值
We'll follow the same process to evaluate state Y.
我们将按照相同的流程评估状态 Y
And you'll notice that state Y appears more than once in
你将发现状态 Y 在每个阶段出现了多次
each episode and it's not quite clear what to do in this case.
这种情况不太清楚该如何处理
To address this, we'll need to define some additional terminology.
为了解决这一问题 我们需要介绍几个其他术语
We define every occurrence of a state in an episode as a visit to that state.
我们将状态在某个阶段中的每次访问定义为该状态的访问
And in the event where a state is visited,
如果状态在某个阶段中访问了多次
more than once in an episode we have two options.
我们有两种处理方式
As a first option,
第一种方式是
we could for each episode only consider
在每个阶段 我们只考虑该状态的首次访问
the first visit to the state and average those returns.
并对这些回报取平均值
In this case, the value of state Y would be estimated as the average of three,
在这种情况下 状态 Y 的值估算为
three and one or seven third's.
3 加 3 再加 1 的平均值 即 3/7
If we choose this approach,
如果采用这种方式
then we say that we are using the first visit MC method.
则表示我们使用的是首次经历 MC 方法
The other option is to average the return
另一种方式是对所有阶段中
following all visits to state Y in all episodes.
状态 Y 的所有访问之后的回报取平均值
In this case, the value of State Y would
在这种情况下 状态 Y 的值估算为
be estimated as the average of all of these numbers,
所有这些数字的平均值
which can be calculated as fourteen sevenths or two.
结果为 14/7 即 2
You'll soon have the chance to implement this algorithm for yourself.
很快你将有机会自己实现该算法
Feel free to choose either first visit or every visit MC prediction,
你可以选择首次经历或所有经历 MC 预测方法
or if you like, implement both.
也可以同时实现这两种方式